Matthew James Slopecki

Profile

I am a highly dedicated, motivated, and focused student, shown through my achievement of a 1st class BSc degree (4.0 GPA equivalent), a current 4.0 GPA in my graduate studies, my undertaking of a 1-year unpaid placement and recently fast-tracking into a PhD.

Education

September 2019 – Present McGill University - Montreal, Canada

- Present PhD Kinesiology Sciences (4.0 GPA)
 - o EDKP 661a Current Topics in Kinesiology (A), EDKP 619 Seminar in K&PE 3 (P)
 - Currently completing collaborative research projects with the University of Tel Aviv and University of Cagliari.
- M.Sc. Completed Courses (4.0 GPA; Fast-tracked into PhD after MSc year one):
 - EDKP 566 Advanced Biomechanics Theory (A), EDKP 605 Research Methods (A),
 EDPE 676 Intermediate Statistics (A), EDKP 604D1 Individual Reading Course 1
 (W), EDKP 616 Individual Reading Course 2 (2), EDKP 672 Advanced
 Experimental Problems (A), EDKP 617 Seminar in K&PE 1 (P), EDKP 618 Seminar in K&PE 2 (P)

September 2015 – June 2019 Brunel University London

- B.Sc. (Honors) in Sport, Health and Exercise Sciences (Human Performance) 1st Class Degree
- Fourth Year Result: 1st
 - Completed Courses: Major Project (A), Physiology of the High Performance Athlete (A-), Applying Sports Sciences to Practice: Training Principles (A*), Employability and Professional Development (A), Biomechanical Analysis Techniques (A-), Human Performance Synoptic Assessment (A-), Issues in Physical Activity, Health and Wellbeing (A-), Applied Sport and Exercise Psychology (A)
- Third Year Result: 1st
 - Industrial Placement at Sports Surgery Clinic Dublin, Republic of Ireland (detailed below under Professional Experience)
 - o Industrial Placement Year Courses: Oral Presentation (A*), Written Assignment (B).
- Second Year Result: 1st
 - o Exchange Year at San Francisco State University as detailed below.
- First Year Result: 1st
 - Completed Courses: Fundamentals of Sport, Health and Exercise Sciences (A),
 Research and Learning Skills (B), Physical Education and Sport Pedagogy (B+),
 Social Sciences of Sport (A*), PA, Health and Wellbeing (B+), Synoptic Study (A).

August 2016 – June 2017 San Francisco State University (SFSU)

- Completed an exchange year studying **B.Sc. Kinesiology**
- Second Year Result: 1st
- Modules: KIN 730 Advanced Biomechanics (M.Sc. Class) (A), KIN 485 Biomechanics (A), KIN 482 Exercise Physiology Lecture (A) and Lab (A-), KIN 486 Motor Learning (A), KIN

331 Peak Performance (A), KIN 504 Sport & Exercise Psychology (A), KIN 355 Science, Sport and Fitness (B+), and KIN 350 Introduction to Kinesiology (C-).

Other Education

- Completed "Python for Data Science and Machine Learning Bootcamp" via Udemy (12/2020)
- Completed "Programming for Everybody (Getting Started in Python)" qualification from University of Michigan via Coursera (08/2017).
- Completed "Introduction to MATLAB" qualification from Vanderbilt University via Coursera (06/2017).
- UKCC Level 2 Rugby Union Coach (08/2016)

Professional Experience

Institut du Sport National du Quebec (Montréal, Canada) – Multiple Roles (11/2019 – present)

- Research Assistant **Data science** / **programming** role to innovate in-house MATLAB application for athlete testing (improving UI and code integration with databases).
- Research Assistant Processing of data for water polo throwing **machine learning** project.
- Volunteer Aided PI with **IMU data collection** for national team water polo athletes.

McGill University (Montréal, Canada) – Teaching Assistant (01/2020 – present)

Lecturing, grading, and administration of EDKP 444 – Ergonomics (Fall 2020); EDKP 208
 Biomechanics and Motor Control (Winter 2020)

McGill University (Montréal, Canada) – Grader (01/2020 – present)

• **Grading** assignments for EDKP 433 – Research Methods

Sports Surgery Clinic (Dublin, Ireland) – Biomechanics Internship (07/2017 – 06/2018)

- 1-year Biomechanics internship in a 3D motion capture lab focused on ACL, Groin and Shoulder rehabilitation, performance testing and research
- Tested patients, ranging from amateur to world class athletes.
- Experience: 350+ hours experience using a 12-camera (VICON) 3d optical motion capture lab with AMTI force plates. Extensive experience performing a range of isokinetic dynamometry tests; including knee, ankle, and shoulder movements. I have developed proficiency at processing data in VICON Nexus and MATLAB, developing novel, custom written codes when necessary for academic research use.

Manuscripts and Publications

- **Slopecki, M.,** Hasanbarani, F., Yang, C., Bailey, C., Côté. J. N. (In Progress). *Uncontrolled manifold analysis of different fatigue locations during a repetitive upper-limb task. In preparation for submission to* Motor Control.
- Hasanbarani, F., Yang, C., **Slopecki, M.,** Bailey, C., Côté. J. N. (In Progress). *The effect of fatigue and sex on motor equivalence values during a fatiguing, repetitive upper-limb task. In preparation for submission to* Journal of Biomechanics.

- Bailey, C., Hasanbarani, F., **Slopecki, M.,** Yang, C., Côté. J. N. (In Progress). *Uncontrolled manifold analysis of sex and age effects during a fatiguing, repetitive upper-limb task. In preparation for submission to* Journal of Motor Behavior..
- **Slopecki, M.,** Messing, K., & Côté, J. N. (2020). Is sex a proxy for mechanical variables during an upper limb repetitive movement task? An investigation of the effects of sex and of anthropometric load on muscle fatigue. *Biology of sex differences*, 11(1). https://doi.org/10.1186/s13293-020-00336-1
- Fanning, C., **Slopecki, M.,** Daniels, K., (In Progress). *Shoulder joint position sense in a clinical population*. No journal/anticipated submission date currently.

Conference and Symposium Presentations

- **Slopecki, M.** (2021). *Motor Variability of the Shoulder: Advanced Metrics*. Presentation given at the 1st Virtual Symposium on Upper Limb Fatigue. Montreal, Canada.
- **Slopecki, M.,** Hasanbarani, F., Bailey, C., Yang, C., Côté. J. N. (Submitted). *Uncontrolled manifold analysis of effects of different fatigue locations on coordination during a repetitive pointing task*. Paper submitted for presentation to 28th Congress of the International Society of Biomechanics, Stockholm, Sweden.
- **Slopecki, M.,** Côté. J. N. (Accepted). *Interaction effect of anthropometric load and sex on the progession of fatigue during an upper limb repetitive movement task.* Paper accepted for presentation to 11th Annual International Conference of Applied Human Factors and Ergonomics, San Diego, USA.
- **Slopecki, M.,** Côté. J. N. (2020). *Quantifying the magnitude of sex differences in kinematic characteristics of an upper-limb repetitive pointing task.* Paper accepted to 21st Biennial Meeting of Canadian Society of Biomechanics, Montreal, Canada.
- **Slopecki, M.,** Daniels, K., Fanning, E., Falvey, E. (2018, September). *The role of torque in shoulder joint position sense.* Paper presented at Royal College of Surgeons Ireland Return to Play: The Shoulder, Dublin, Ireland.

Knowledge Translation Initiatives

 Presentation give at Center for Interdisciplinary Research in Rehabilitation – Talking Research series: "Is sex a proxy for anthropometric variables during fatiguing, upper-limb repetitive movement? What researchers and clinicians should know"

Service Experience

Ad-hoc Peer-Review:

- Independent reviewer for Applied Ergonomics, Current Research in Physiology
- Contributed to reviews for Ergonomics, Applied Ergonomics

Academic Funding

Fellowships and Scholarships

 Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR) Team for Gender Considerations in Knowledge Transfer Interventions – pour le partage des connaissances scholarship 2020 (\$6,000)

Awards

- Mitacs GlobalLink Research Award Abroad 2021
- McGill University Graduate Excellence Award 2020 2023
- McGill University Graduate Excellence Award 2020
- McGill University GREAT Travel Award 2020
- REPAR Travel Award Support for Students for Presentation in Scientific Events 2019-2020
- Department of Kinesiology and Physical Education Recruitment Award 2019 2020 (McGill University)

Stipends

- Research Stipend from Dr. Julie N. Côté's Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada Grant 2021 - 2023)
- Research Stipend from Dr. Julie N. Côté's McGill Sports Science Research Grant 2020 -2021
- Research Stipend from Dr. Julie N. Côté's Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada Grant 2020 – 2021
- Research Stipend from Dr. Julie N. Côté's Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada Grant 2020-2021
- Research Stipend from Dr. Julie N. Côté's Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada Grant 2019-2020

Memberships

- Canada Sport Scientist Student Member 02/2021 Present
- International Society of Biomechanics (ISB) 12/2020 Present
- Center for Interdisciplinary Research in Rehabilitation (CRIR) 09/2019 Present
- Quebec Rehabilitation Research Network (REPAR) 09/2019 Present

Additional Achievements and Qualifications

- VP of Communication on the Kinesiology and Physical Education Graduate Students Committee Fall 2020 - Present
- Jack Petchey Outstanding Achiever Award 2012
- PADI Open Water Scuba Diver
- Grade 8 Acoustic Guitar, Grade 5 Electric Guitar
- Full UK driving license with experience towing trailers.

Skills

• **Communication** – Effective communication skills through hundreds of hours of patient testing where it is critical to effectively share key points of information with patients to ensure they understand the tasks at hand. This is also shown through my coaching experience, reflected

by my UKCC Level 2 in coaching rugby union.

- **Time Management** Working in a rehabilitation clinic with rigid time constraints for appointments developed my ability to prioritize time.
- **Leadership** Leading international collaborative research projects with Tel Aviv University and University of Cagliari has greatly developed my ability to lead groups of people.

• Software and Programming Knowledge

- o Experienced in use of motion capture software (VICON Nexus, Cortex).
- o Proficient in MATLAB, Python and SQL for data science
 - Analysis using novel codes
 - Machine Learning algorithms (Supervised, Unsupervised, (Deep) Neural Networks)
 - Advanced and interactive data visualization.
 - Database integration through APIs.
 - GUIs using MATLAB App Designer and Python Tkinter
- o Experienced using version control software (**GitHub**)
 - Creator of INS Quebec GitHub page
- o Proficient with Microsoft Office.
- o Experienced using statistical analysis software such as IBM SPSS and R

• Laboratory Skills

- Extensive experience setting up and using Isokinetic Dynamometers (Cybex, Biodex), 3d motion capture systems (Vicon, Cortex), force plates (AMTI, PASCO) and EMG systems (Delsys).
- o Experience using Ergometers, Goniometers, Bodpods, ECGs and Skinfold Calipers.
- \circ Introductory experience running a range of physiological testing including VO2_{max}, Wingate, Indirect Calorimetry and Hydrostatic Weighing.

References - available upon request